SIBO is one of the topics I'm asked
about the most and I'm glad I finally
have the chance to dig into the research
in this two-part video series.
I'll be answering the following
questions: Is SIBO real?
How reliable are the diagnostic tests?
Does a low FODMAP diet help?
And if you have SIBO or IBS symptoms,
what should you do about it?
Let's go find out.
"Tests, Fiber, and Low FODMAP for
Small Intestinal Bacterial Overgrowth (SIBO)"
Gastrointestinal symptoms
like abdominal pain
and bloating account for millions
of doctor visits every year.
One of the conditions that may be
considered for such a nonspecific
presentation of symptoms is SIBO:
Small Intestinal Bacterial Overgrowth,
a concept that has gained
popularity on the internet,
in addition to certain clinical
and research circles.
SIBO is broadly defined
as the excessive growth of
bacteria in the small intestine, and
is typically treated with antibiotics.
But dispensing antibiotics to patients
with such nonspecifc, common
symptoms is not without risks.
You could be fostering
antibiotic resistance,
there could be side effects,
and wiping out your good bacteria
could set you up for an invasion
of bad bugs like C. diff,
all for a condition that
may not even be real.
Even alternative medicine
journals admit that SIBO
is being overdiagnosed,
creating confusion and fear.
SIBO testing is overused and
overly relied upon. Diagnoses are
often handed out quickly and
without adequate substantiation.
Patients can be indoctrinated into
thinking SIBO is a chronic condition
that cannot be cleared and will
require lifelong management.
This is simply not true for most and
is an example of the damage done
by overzealousness.
The monster that we now perceive SIBO
to be may be no more than a phantom.
The traditional method for a diagnosis
was a small bowel aspiration,
an invasive test where a long tube
is snaked down your throat
to take a sample and count
the bugs down there.
But this method has been almost
entirely replaced with breath testing.
See, normally, a sugar called glucose
is almost entirely absorbed
in the small intestine, so it never
makes it down to the colon.
So if there is bacterial fermentation
of that sugar, that suggests
you have bacteria up in your
small intestine and can detect
that fermentation because the
bacteria produce specific gases
that get absorbed in your blood stream
and then are breathed out from
your lungs, which can then be detected
with a breathalyzer-type machine.
Previously, a sugar called lactulose
was used, but lactulose breath tests
weren't found to reliably detect
the overgrowth of bacteria,
so researchers switched to glucose.
But when glucose was finally put
to the test, it didn't work either.
The bacterial load in the
small intestine was similar
for those testing positive or negative,
so that's not a useful test either.
It turns out glucose can make it
down to your colon after all.
They labeled the glucose dose with
a tracer and found that almost half
of the positive results from glucose
breath tests were false positives
because they were just fermenting
it down in their colon
where your bacteria are
supposed to be.
So patients incorrectly labeled with
SIBO may undergo multiple courses
of antibiotics for a problem
they don't even have.
Why do experts keep recommending
breath testing then?
Oh, you mean the experts at
the conference supported by
a breath testing company, most of
whom had personally received funds
from SIBO testing
or antibiotic companies?
And even if we could properly
diagnose it, does it even matter?
In those with digestive symptoms,
there is a range of positivity for SIBO
from approximately 4% to 84%
—all over the map—
and there may be no difference in
symptom scores between those testing
positive versus those testing negative,
so testing positive could mean anything.
Who cares if some people have bacteria
growing in their small intestines
if that doesn't necessarily
correlate with symptoms?
Now antibiotics can make people
with irritable bowel-type symptoms
diagnosed with SIBO feel better, so
doesn't that prove SIBO was the cause?
No, because it can make just
as many people feel better
who are negative for SIBO.
Currently rifaximin is most often used
for SIBO, but it's not FDA-approved
for SIBO, so the cost
can be prohibitive.
In fact, no drug has
been approved for SIBO,
so even if you have good
insurance, you may be shelling
out-of-pocket as
much as $50 a day,
and you typically take
it for two weeks.
And while antibiotics may
help in the short-term,
they may make things
worse in the long-term.
Those who are given a course of
antibiotics are more than three times
as likely to report more bowel symptoms
four months later than controls.
So what can we do for
these kinds of symptoms?
That's exactly what I'm
going to turn to next.
If you test more than a thousand
patients suffering from
irritable bowel-type symptoms
such as excess gas, bloating,
diarrhea, abdominal pain
for longer than six months,
who don't appear to have anything
more serious going on, such as
inflammatory bowel disease, a
significant percentage were found
to be suffering from lactose intolerance:
intolerance to the milk sugar lactose.
In infancy we have an enzyme
in our small intestines that
digests milk sugar, but most of us
understandably lose it after weaning.
Although a genetic mutation has
led to the persistence of the enzyme
in a minority of adults, about
75% of the world's population
malabsorb lactose and have
lactose intolerance after age 30.
A third, though, were
diagnosed with SIBO:
Small Intestinal Bacterial Overgrowth.
The evidence for SIBO and IBS
symptoms is shrouded in controversy,
predominantly because of the
fact that the breath tests used
in clinical practice to diagnose
SIBO are not valid,
as I explored in the last video.
And it's not even clear
what the implications are of having
more versus less bacteria growing
in your small intestine since the number
don't seem to correlate with symptoms.
It turns out it's not the
number, but the type.
It's the kind of bugs you have
growing in your small intestine.
So it's small intestinal microbial
dysbiosis, not overgrowth in general,
but the wrong kind of growth
that appears to underlie
symptoms associated with functional
gastrointestinal disorders
like irritable bowel syndrome.
How can you prevent
this from happening?
Well, the symptoms appeared
be correlated to a significant drop
in the number of Prevotella species.
Remember them?
Prevotella are healthy fiber feeders,
suggestive of a higher fiber intake
in healthy individuals, while the bugs
found more in symptomatic patients
ate sugar, which may reflect a
higher dietary intake of sugars.
Yes, but correlation
doesn't mean causation.
To prove cause and effect
you have to put it to the test,
which is exactly what they did.
Switching a group of healthy individuals
who habitually ate a higher fiber diet
to a more typical standard American
low fiber diet with lots of sugar
produced striking results
within just seven days.
First, 80% developed new
gastrointestinal symptoms
out of the blue, such as bloating
and abdominal pain that resolved
on resumption of their more healthful,
habitual higher fiber diet. And the
diet related changes in the small
intestinal microbiome were predictive
of symptoms and linked to an
alteration in intestinal permeability;
in other words, they developed
a leaky gut within seven days.
And while some went from
SIBO positive to SIBO negative,
or SIBO negative
to SIBO positive,
it didn't matter, since the
number of bacteria growing
didn't correlate with symptoms. It
was the type of bacteria growing.
And no wonder their guts got leaky.
Short-chain fatty acid levels plummeted.
Those are the magical by-products that
our good gut bugs make from fiber,
which play an important role
in intestinal barrier integrity,
meaning keeping our gut
from getting leaky. So while
we don't have sound data that
something like a low FODMAP diet
has any benefit for
SIBO-symptom patients,
there have been more than a
dozen randomized controlled trials
putting fiber to the test, and overall
there was a significant improvement
in symptoms among those randomized
to increase their fiber intake.
That may actually help explain
why high-fiber, plant-based diets
may prevent so many common
diseases — the effect such diets have
on the composition and metabolic
activity of our microbiome.
Our good gut bugs take the
plant residues like fiber
and produce health-promoting and
cancer-suppressing metabolites
like those short-chain fatty acids
which have profound
anti-inflammatory properties.
All the evidence points
to a physiological need
for about 50 grams of fiber a day,
which is the amount contained
in the traditional African diet
and associated with the prevention
of westernized diseases.
That's approximately twice
what's typically recommended
and three times more than what
most people are getting day-to-day.
Perhaps it should be no
surprise we need so much.
Even though we split from
chimpanzees millions of years ago,
there's still broad congruency
in the composition
of our respective microbiomes
to this day.
While they're still eating their 98-99%
plant-based diets to feed their friendly
flora with fiber, we've largely removed
fiber-rich foods from our food supply.